BU Records: NoZe Brotherhood, Inclusive: 1929-2022; Bulk: 1941-2022
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: NoZe Brotherhood
Inclusive: 1929-2022; Bulk: 1941-2022
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/384
NoZe Brotherhood (Waco, Tex.)
2 document boxes and 4 oversized boxes.
BU Records: NoZe Brotherhood consists of original copies of The Rope newspaper, clippings, and administrative documents produced by and written about the NoZe Brotherhood, an unofficial, satirical, and secret society at Baylor University.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The Nose Brothers were founded in the 1920s as a rival to the Baylor Chamber of Commerce and as a satire on men’s social organizations. Although the exact date of the organization’s founding is disputed, it is the oldest men’s social organization at Baylor University. Its annual gala, The Pink Tea, dates back to 1926. The organization has gone by a number of names, including The Nosemen of Truth, The Most Noble Nose Brotherhood of Baylor Barber College, the Nose Brotherhood of the Universe, Unlimited, and, currently, The NoZe Brotherhood. NoZe was spelled with a capitalized “z” after 1965.
The NoZe Brotherhood is governed by "The Book of Holy Law," which stipulates the structure of the organization as well as standards of conduct for its members. All members of the organization adopt humorous, nose-related pseudonyms. Members of the organization were originally called “Nosemen” and are currently called Brothers. The Brotherhood became a secret society in the mid-1960s. Currently, brothers “undress” (wear costumes, often wigs, glasses, and beards or mustaches) to keep their identities hidden.
The NoZe Brotherhood publishes The Rope, a now-monthly newspaper that satirizes a wide variety of subjects, including Baylor University, politicians, Waco, and Christianity. Throughout the 1940s, humorous articles written by members of the Nose Brotherhood were published in The Lariat, Baylor University’s student newspaper. The NoZe Brotherhood began publishing its own satirical, monthly newspaper circa 1950.
Throughout its history, the NoZe Brotherhood has had numerous conflicts with Baylor University administration. The Brotherhood was banned in 1965 when they painted pink and possibly set fire to a bridge over Waco Creek. In December 1978, Baylor University President Abner McCall banned the Brotherhood for publishing and distributing a counterfeit Lariat. In 1999, The Rope parodied a study-abroad program using racial stereotypes, and the Brotherhood was subsequently kicked off campus when it refused to register with the University as a formal organization. Currently, the NoZe Brotherhood is not an official student organization at Baylor University.
Scope and Content
This collection begins in 1929 and ends in 2022. It contains documents produced by and about the NoZe Brotherhood, an unofficial, satirical, and secret society at Baylor University. Series I. Administrative, includes the governing document of the Brotherhood, "The Book of the Holy Law," as well as agreements between Baylor University and the Brotherhood. Series II. Clippings, includes articles about the NoZe Brotherhood published by the Baylor Lariat, the Baylor Line, the Waco Tribune-Herald, the Dallas Morning News, the Houston Chronicle, the Texas Monthly, Esquire, and others. Series III. Correspondence, contains letters and postcards to and from the Brotherhood. The bulk of this collection is Series IV. Literary Productions, which contains advertisements, original artwork, Pink Tea programs, and copies of The Rope Newspaper..
Some materials in the collection were compiled over time by previous Texas Collection staff members and kept in subject files. These materials were added to the collection during processing.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, this collection was arranged in four large boxes, one legal-paper sized box, and twelve subject files. The four large boxes contained The Rope newspapers, organized chronologically; the legal-paper sized box contained a photocopied version of the book, The Nose Brotherhood Knows (1997), clippings, screenplays, drawings (undated), one microfilm container, and one flash drive; the twelve subject folders contained clippings, artwork, and Baylor University press releases, organized chronologically by decade (1920s-2000s).
The current arrangement is as follows: Series I. Administrative, Series II. Clippings, Series III. Correspondence, and Series IV. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/384.
Related Resources
Related references
England, Mark. “The NoZe Knows No Bounds.” Waco Tribune-Herald, 1997 February 8.
Long, William Bowman and Long, Mary Cole Farrow, eds. The Nose Brotherhood Knows: A Collection of Nothings and Non-Happenings, 1926-1965. Belton, TX: Davis Brothers Publishing Company, Inc., 1997.
"Student Organizations." Accessed 2017 December 12.
“The NoZe Knows Which Way Is Up.” Baylor Magazine, 2003 May/June, Vol. 1, No. 6.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Societies, etc.; Baylor University -- Students.
Subjects
Advertisements.; College students -- Texas -- Waco -- Societies, etc.; Correspondence. gmgpc
Genres
Baylor University -- Newspapers.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Newspapers.; Programs (Publications).
- Administrative, 1970-1995; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  This series is arranged chronologically. It contains a 1970 sociology paper on the organizational structure of the Brotherhood; a proposed, 1984 agreement between Baylor University and the Brotherhood; and a 1995 copy of "The Book of the Holy Law." This series is in excellent condition.
  - An Organizational Analysis of the NoZe Brotherhood, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agreement Between Baylor University and the NoZe Brotherhood, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Book of the Holy Law, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1931-2009; 2
  General condition: Good.
  This series is arranged chronologically by decade. It contains newspaper and magazine clippings about the NoZe Brotherhood. This series is in good condition.
  - Clippings, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1941-circa 1996; 3
  This series contains correspondence to and from members of the NoZe Brotherhood. This series is in excellent condition.
  - Correspondence, 1941-circa 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Literary Productions, circa 1941-2022; 4
  This series is organized alphabetically, except the folders containing The Rope, which were placed at the end of the series in order to ensure room for continued expansion. This series is in good condition.
  - Advertisements, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advertisements, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Advertisements, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Advertisements, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Advertisements, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Advertisements, 2000-2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Advertisements, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Annual Christmas Party, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Artwork, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Nose Brotherhood Knows, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pink Tea, 1929-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Pink Tea, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pink Tea, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pink Tea, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pink Tea, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pink Tea, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pink Tea, 2000-2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rose NoZe Campaign, circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Screenplays, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Screenplay Storyboard Notes, circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Rope, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Rope, circa 1941 Fall (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Rope, 1951 Fall (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Rope, 1954 Spring (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Rope, 1955 Spring (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Rope, 1956 Fall (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Rope, 1957 Spring (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Rope, 1957 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - The Rope, 1957 Fall (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Rope, 1960 Fall (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Rope, 1961 Spring (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Rope, 1962 Fall (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Rope, 1964 Fall (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Rope, 1966 Fall (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Rope, 1967 Fall (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Rope, 1977 Spring (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Rope, 1977 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - The Rope, 1978 Fall (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Rope, 1979 Spring (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Rope, 1979 Fall (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Rope, 1979 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - The Rope, 1980 Spring (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Rope, 1980 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - The Rope, 1980 Spring (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Rope, 1980 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - The Rope, 1981 Spring (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The Rope, 1981 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - The Rope, 1981 Fall (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The Rope, 1981 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 7)
  - The Rope, 1982 Spring (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - The Rope, 1982 Fall (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Rope, 1982 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 8)
  - The Rope, 1983 Spring (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The Rope, 1983 Fall (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - The Rope, 1983 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 9)
  - The Rope, 1984 Spring (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - The Rope, 1984 Fall (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - The Rope, 1984 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 10)
  - The Rope, 1985 Spring (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - The Rope, 1985 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 11)
  - The Rope, 1985 Fall (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - The Rope, 1986 Spring (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The Rope, 1986 Fall (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - The Rope, 1987 Spring (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Rope, 1987 Fall (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - The Rope, 1988 Spring (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - The Rope, 1988 Fall (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - The Rope, 1988 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 12)
  - The Rope, 1989 Spring (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - The Rope, 1989 Fall (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - The Rope, 1989 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 13)
  - The Rope, 1990 Spring (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - The Rope, 1990 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 14)
  - The Rope, 1990 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 15)
  - The Rope, 1991 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 16)
  - The Rope, 1991 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 17)
  - The Rope, 1992 Spring (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Rope, 1992 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 18)
  - The Rope, 1993 Spring (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Rope, 1993 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 19)
  - The Rope, 1993 Fall (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Rope, 1994 Spring (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Rope, 1994 Fall (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Rope, 1995 Spring (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Rope, 1995 Fall (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Rope, 1996 Spring (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Rope, 1996 Fall (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Rope, 1997 Spring (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Rope, 1997 Fall (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Rope, 1998 Spring (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - v, 1998 Fall (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Rope, 1999 Spring (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - The Rope, 1999 Fall (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - The Rope, 2000 Spring (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - The Rope, 2000 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 20)
  - The Rope, 2001 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 21)
  - The Rope, 2001 Fall (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Rope, 2002 Spring (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Rope, 2002 Fall (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Rope, 2003 Spring (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - The Rope, 2003 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 22)
  - The Rope, 2003 Fall (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - The Rope, 2003 Fall (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 23)
  - The Rope, 2004 Spring (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - The Rope, 2004 Fall (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - The Rope, 2005 Spring (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - The Rope, 2005 Fall (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - The Rope, 2006 Spring (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - The Rope, 2006 Spring (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 24)
  - The Rope, 2006 Fall (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Rope, 2007 Spring (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Rope, 2007 Fall (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Rope, 2008 Spring (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Rope, 2008 Fall (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Rope, 2009 Spring (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Rope, 2009 Fall (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Rope, 2010 Spring (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Rope, 2010 Fall (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Rope, 2011 Spring (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Rope, circa 2011 Summer (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Rope, 2011 Fall (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Rope, 2012 Spring (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Rope, 2012 Fall (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Rope, 2013 Spring (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - The Rope, 2013 Fall (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - The Rope, circa 2013-2014 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - The Rope, 2014 Spring (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - The Rope, 2014 Fall (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - The Rope, 2015 Fall (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Rope, 2017 Spring (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - The Rope, 2017 Fall (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - The Rope, 2018 Spring (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - The Rope, 2018 Fall (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - The Rope, 2019 Spring (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - The Rope, 2019 Fall (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - The Rope, 2020 Spring (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - The Rope, 2020 Fall (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - The Rope, 2021 Spring (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - The Rope, 2021 Fall (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - The Rope, 2022 Spring (Box 5, Folder 31)